Actuarial Science (CBA)

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Actuarial Science (CBA)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (28 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR: Susan Vagts

DESCRIPTION

Director and Associate Professor of Practice: Susan Vagts

Professor: Ramsay

Associate Professor: Mashayekhi

Assistant Professors: Liu, Xu

Assistant Professor of Practice: Clemens

An actuary is a mathematically-oriented business person who will most likely be a manager or supervisor at some point in his/her career. Thus, a course of study culminating in a bachelor of science degree in business administration with a major in actuarial science is an excellent educational background for prospective actuaries. Additional information is available at www.BeAnActuary.org.

The actuarial science program is designed to prepare students for the current industry demands. Because the demands change on a regular basis, often times, the number of hours, the sequencing of courses, and the specific requirements change for this major. Students should continue to consult with the department for the appropriate selection and listing of course requirements.

The actuarial science program is proud to have been named one of the first Centers of Actuarial Excellence by the Society of Actuaries.

All actuarial science students are encouraged to visit the actuarial science program’s website (http://cba.unl.edu/academics/actuarial/) and an actuarial science program faculty advisor for more information about the program, including the Actuarial Science Club, sequencing of courses, scholarship opportunities, and the requirements for achieving professional actuarial designations.

In addition, because of the mathematical orientation for this program, actuarial science majors are required to make some modifications to the degree program requirements. These requirements (with a reminder that all required course work must be taken for a grade) are noted below.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 28 hours of course work for the major.

As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.

Actuarial science majors must take MATH 106, MATH 107, and MATH 208, as well as CSCE 101 & CSCE 101L. These hours have been built into the College Degree Requirements as part of the Non-Business Requirements (NBR).

ACTS 399/ACTS 499 may not count toward the major or minor in actuarial science.

Other College Degree Requirement changes for actuarial science majors include:

ACTS majors must take STAT 380 in place of ECON 215 for the Business Core Foundation (BCF) requirements.
ACTS majors will also take STAT 462 & STAT 463 Introduction to Mathematical Statistics I & II for the Business Core Foundation (BCF) requirements.
ACTS majors will take FINA 461 Advanced Finance in place of FINA 361 for the Business Core Intermediate (BCI) requirements; the prerequisite of FINA 361 (for FINA 363 and FINA 461) is satisfied with completion of ACTS 440.
12 hours of 300/400-level elective course work is NOT required for actuarial science majors.

As part of the college elective requirements, all students complete ONE business elective course for the program. ACTS majors are WAIVED from this specific requirement; however, all ACTS majors must take an IBCR course and thus, this can be done to meet the business elective requirement. The department suggests ECON 321 or MNGT 414 as part of NBR 6–ACE 9 which then double counts for both the NBR 6 and IBCR requirement. An alternative option is to take FINA 450 International Financial Management to meet the IBCR (FINA 450 can double count towards a finance major or finance minor).

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

Requirements for students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in actuarial science will complete 28 hours of actuarial science course work for the Business Core Advanced-Major (BCA-M):

Requirements 28

ACTS 430 Actuarial Applications of Applied Statistics 3

ACTS 440 Interest Theory 4

ACTS 470 Life Contingencies I 3

ACTS 471 Life Contingencies II 3

ACTS 473 Introduction to Risk Theory 3

ACTS 475 Actuarial Applications in Practice 3

FINA 338 Principles of Individual & Corporate Risk Management 3

FINA 363 Investment Principles 3

Choose one of the following: 3

ACTS 410 Introduction to Credibility, Smoothing of Data & Simulation (3 hr)

ACTS 425 Survival Models (3 hr)

ACTS 450 Stochastic Processes for Actuaries (3 hr)

ACTS 474 Introduction to Property/Casualty Actuarial Science (3 hr)

FINA 467 Options, Futures & Derivative Securities (3 hr)

In addition to the 28 hours for the major, ACTS majors are also encouraged to take:

ACTS 441 Introduction to Financial Economics (3 hr)

ACTS 474 Introduction to Property/Casualty Actuarial Science (3 hr)

Actuarial science problem labs as appropriate

MATH 314 Linear Algebra (3 hr)

MATH 221 Differential Equations (3 hr)

At least one of:

FINA 412 Life & Health Insurance (3 hr)

FINA 420 Employee Benefit Plans (3 hr)

FINA 438 Enterprise Risk Management (3 hr)

ECON 413 Social Insurance (FINA 413) (3 hr)

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

While not required, actuarial science majors may double major in finance. The finance department allows double counting of courses for students choosing to obtain a double major in actuarial science and finance.

Actuarial Science and Finance Double Majors

1. Take the Core Finance Requirements.

FINA 363 Investment Principles (3 hr)

FINA 365 Financial Institutions (ECON 365) (3 hr)

FINA 367 Fixed Income Investments (3 hr)

FINA 461 Advanced Finance (3 hr)

FINA 475 Strategic Financial Managment (3 hr)

2. Select ONLY ONE of the three options available.

Banking and Risk Managment

CFA Investment

General Finance

Finance Minor

Actuarial students may double count their finance courses towards a finance minor. They will follow the regular minor found in the finance section of the Bulletin. The courses used might include:

Two of the following:

FINA 363 Investment Principles (3 hr)

FINA 365 Financial Institutions (ECON 365) (3 hr)

FINA 367 Fixed Income Investments (3 hr)

Select one 300/400 level from:

FINA 338 Principles of Individual & Corporate Risk Management (3 hr)

FINA 412 Life & Health Insurance (3 hr)

FINA 438 Enterprise Risk Management (3 hr)

FINA 465 Bank Management (3 hr)

FINA 467 Options, Futures & Derivative Securities (3 hr)

or one of FINA 363, FINA365 or FINA 367 (if not taken above)

Select one 400 level:

FINA 461 Advanced Finance (3 hr)

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Actuarial Science Minor

To fulfill the requirements for an actuarial science minor, students must complete:

Twelve (12) graded hours of actuarial science course work; ACTS 440, ACTS 441, ACTS 470, and ACTS 474 are suggested.
No "Pass/No Pass"
ACTS 399 may not be used toward the minor (or major).
The college requires that 75% of the minor be earned on campus.

OTHER

Actuarial Science Major

All course work for the major must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass).

Substitutions When Changing Majors

If ACTS students change to a different major in the College of Business Administration, the following substitutions may be made.

ACTS 440 for FINA 361

STAT 380 for ECON 215

Anthropology

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Anthropology

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR: Dr. Martha McCollough

DESCRIPTION

Chair: LuAnn Wandsnider, 816 Oldfather Hall

Professors: Hames, Wandsnider

Associate Professors: Athanassopoulos, McCollough

Assistant Professors: Heitman, Richards-Rissetto

Assistant Professors of Practice: Babchuk, Hammerl

Lecturer: Douglass

Courtesy Faculty: Gibson (College of Business Administration), Hamann (College of Education and Human Sciences), Reinhard (School of Natural Resources), Sarroub (College of Education and Human Sciences)

Research Faculty: Hartley, Hunt, Scott

Adjunct Faculty: Dempsey, Rippiteau, Rissetto, Schilling

Undergraduate Advisor: Dr. Martha McCollough, 402-472-2441, mmccollough1@unl.edu

The Department of Anthropology synthesizes humanistic and scientific perspectives on human biological and cultural diversity as well as the evolutionary trends seen for humankind. Students and faculty bring this integrated perspective to interactions and collaborations with others in a variety of departments and programs in each of the Colleges across the University.

Courses in anthropology acquaint students with the range of human behavior as differentially explored within each of the subdisciplines within Anthropology--archaeology, biological anthropology, and cultural anthropology. Methodological courses outfit students with valuable analytic and research skills in qualitative, quantitative and GIS analysis as well as in content-appropriate analytic protocols, as for the analysis of archaeological and ethnographic materials.

We value the synergy that comes from working between the subdisciplines of Anthropology. This synergy is realized in our integrated approach to Digital Cultural Heritage, which is the application of information technologies to advance research in the broadly construed and highly interdisciplinary area of culture heritage. Our faculty has special expertise in the development, application, and distribution of content and technologies in Digital Cultural Heritage.

Our Department offers a field school in archeology annually and we help students identify internship opportunities in the city of Lincoln, Nebraska, and the United States. Students have interned at the Smithsonian and at museums and national agencies throughout the United States. In Lincoln, students have completed internships with the Asian Community and Cultural Center, the Indian Center, the National Park Service Midwest Archeological Center (one of two major NPS research laboratories) and the People’s City Mission, to name a few.

Recommendations. Because of the broad and interdisciplinary nature of anthropology, we recommend that majors select additional courses outside the department to enhance their appreciation of and improve their skills in related disciplines. The student’s advisor will make specific course recommendations in keeping with individual needs and interests. See also online Career Paths.

Graduate Work. The Department of Anthropology offers graduate work leading to the master of arts degree. A description of the program appears in the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

Graduate Advisor: Dr. Effie Athanassopoulos, 402-472-0172, eathanassopoulos1@unl.edu

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Anthropology (31 hours)

Foundation Courses 10

ANTH 212 Introduction to Cultural Anthropology (ETHN 212) 3

ANTH 232 Introduction to Prehistory 3

ANTH 242 & ANTH 242L Introduction to Biological Anthropology & Lab 4

Advanced Anthropology Courses 9

Archaeology 3

Select one course from:

ANTH 337 Archaeology of the American Southwest (3 hrs)

ANTH 386 Digital Heritage Tools (3 hrs)

ANTH 431 Historical Archaeology: Current Topics (3 hrs)

ANTH 432 History & Theory of Archaeology (3 hrs)

ANTH 433 North American Archaeology (3 hrs)

ANTH 434 Introduction to Great Plains Archaeology (3 hrs)

ANTH 436 The Ancient Maya (LAMS 436) (3 hrs)

ANTH 438 Topics in Old World Prehistory (CLAS 438) (3 hrs)

Biological Anthropology 3

Select one course from:

ANTH 344 Human Osteology (4 hrs)

ANTH 374 Primate Behavior & Ecology (3 hrs)

ANTH 385 Human Origins (3 hrs)

ANTH 422 Medical Anthropology (3 hrs)

ANTH 442 Human Variation (3 hrs)

ANTH 430 Nutritional Anthropology (NUTR 430) (3 hrs)

ANTH 443 Dental Anthropology (3 hrs)

ANTH 448 Human Growth & Development (BIOS 448) (3 hrs)

Cultural Anthropology 3

Select one course from:

ANTH 350 Peoples & Cultures of Latin America (ETHN 350) (3 hrs)

ANTH 351 Indigenous Peoples of North America (ETHN 351) (3 hrs)

ANTH 352 Indigenous Peoples of the Great Plains(ETHN 352) (3 hrs)

ANTH 353 Anthropology of War (3 hrs)

ANTH 362 Peoples & Cultures of Africa (ETHN 362) (3 hrs)

ANTH 366 Peoples & Cultures of East Asia (ETHN 366) (3 hrs)

ANTH 410 Gender: An Anthropological Perspective (WMNS 410) (3 hrs)

ANTH 412 Family, Marriage, & Kinship (3 hrs)

*ANTH 416 Digital Anthropologies (3 hrs)

*ANTH 417 History of Anthropological Theory (3 hrs)

ANTH 418 Ethnology & Museums (3 hrs)

ANTH 419 Art & Anthropology of Native North Americans (3 hrs)

ANTH 451 Contemporary Issues of Indigenous Peoples in North America (3 hrs)

ANTH 472 Belief Systems in Anthropological Perspective (3 hrs)

ANTH 473 Ecological Anthropology (3 hrs)

*ANTH 474 Applied & Development Anthropology (3 hrs)

ANTH 477 Hunters-Gatherers (3 hrs)

*ANTH 488 Contentious Issues in Anthropology (3 hrs)

Research Methods 3

Select one course from:

ANTH 290 Fieldwork (3 hrs)

ANTH 384 Quantitative Methods in Anthropology (3 hrs)

ANTH 389 GIS in Archaeology (3 hrs)

ANTH 390 Field School in Archaeology (3 hrs)

ANTH 406 Visualization & the Ancient City (AHIS 406) (3 hrs)

ANTH 461 Geospatial Approaches in the Digital Humanities & Social Sciences (3 hrs)

ANTH 482 Field Methods in Ethnography (3 hrs)

ANTH 487 Analysis of Archaeological Materials A-E (3 hrs)

ANTH 490 Advanced Field Work (3 hrs)

ANTH 491 Advanced Laboratory Work (3 hrs)

Electives 9

Select courses from: 100-, 200-, 300-, or 400- series.

Integrative coursework is recommended. Courses above with asterisk integrate knowledge from each of the subdisciplines of Anthropology.

Fieldwork is recommended. Only 6 credits total of ANTH 290, 390, and ANTH 490 may count toward the major. Only 3 credits of ANTH 291 or ANTH 491 may count toward the major.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its program, majors will, as they complete an ACE 10 course in their junior or senior year:

1. Participate in a focus group discussion of programmatic strengths and weaknesses.

2. Complete an exit survey, submitted anonymously.

Results of participation in these assessment activities will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

Graduate Work. Students contemplating graduate work should work closely with advisor to design course of study.

Minor Requirements

A minor may be chosen from any minor offered by the College of Arts and Sciences.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

No course may be taken Pass/No Pass.

Course Level Requirement

At least 12 hourse in courses numbered in the 300 and 400 series. May be satisfied by courses from the Advanced Anthropology Course list or the Research Methods course list.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Requires 18 hours of anthropology including ANTH 110; at least one of the 200-level core courses in anthropology (ANTH 212 Introduction to Cultural Anthropology (ETHN 212), ANTH 232 Introduction to Archaeology, or ANTH 242 Introduction to Biological Anthropology); and, at least one 300- or 400-level anthropology course. Up to 6 hours of field study (ANTH 290, ANTH 291, ANTH 490, ANTH 491) courses may apply. Excluded courses: ANTH 130.

Construction Management

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Construction Management

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Construction Management

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.4 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR: Garrett Gassman (Omaha), Kevin Sueper (Lincoln)

DESCRIPTION

Durham School of Architectural Engineering and Construction

School Director: Jay Puckett

Program Coordinator: Kevin Grosskopf

Professors: Goedert, Grosskopf

Associate Professors: Bernstein, Bonsell, Fischer, Jensen, Schwer, Shen, Stentz, Wentz

Assistant Professors: Ahn, Esmaeili, Woldesenbet

Assistant Professor of Practice: Bowen

Industry Fellow: Cuddigan

Industry Relations: Downey

Construction management (CNST) is a complete undergraduate degree program available to students within The Charles W. Durham School of Architectural Engineering and Construction located at Nebraska Hall on the Lincoln City Campus and at the Peter Kiewit Institute (PKI) in Omaha. Construction is one of the largest and most diversified industries in the country, accounting for approximately 4 percent of the U.S. gross domestic product (GDP). The key professional in this vast enterprise is the “constructor,” a term given to leaders and managers in the construction industry who are responsible for planning, scheduling and building the projects designed by architects and engineers. These highly specialized efforts are indispensable in meeting the country’s growing need for new structures, infrastructure, and environmental controls that are of high quality, and are cost effective, efficient, and sustainable.

Construction firms vary in size from large corporations to small proprietorships and partnerships. These are often classified according to the kind of construction work they do: general contractors, heavy and highway contractors, specialty contractors—including mechanical and electrical—and residential builders and developers. Many firms engage in more than one category of work. Some larger companies incorporate the architectural and engineering design functions as part of their role as a design/build firm. Collectively, constructors manufacture our entire built environment—buildings for housing, commerce and industry, highways, railroads, waterways, airports, power plants, energy distribution systems, military bases and space center complexes. Thus, the construction management field is broad, requiring a unique educational background for its professional practitioners.

Although the range of construction activities appears wide and diverse, the general educational requirements for construction management are universal regardless of a particular firm’s area of specialization. Since construction is primarily a business enterprise, the graduate must have a sound background in business management and administration, as well as an understanding of the fundamentals of architecture and engineering as they relate to project design and the actual construction process in the field. Professional expertise lies in the fields of construction science, methods, and management. A working knowledge of structural design, mechanical and electrical systems, methods and materials, soil mechanics, and construction equipment is also essential.

The construction management curriculum embraces a course of study in specifications, contractual agreements, labor relations, personnel management, materials, methods, and work analysis techniques. Technical and humanities electives provide a well-rounded education that leads to a rewarding career in the construction industry.

The long-term program educational objectives are to produce graduates who, as leaders in the field:

Specify project objectives and plans including delineation of scope, budget, and schedule;
Select project participants and set performance requirements;
Maximize resource efficiency through judicious procurement of labor, materials and equipment;
Implement and complete construction activities through coordination and control of scheduling, contracting, estimating and cost;
Develop effective communication protocols and mechanisms for resolving conflicts associated with the construction process;
Ensure quality through design, measurement, analysis, and control.
Engage in lifelong learning which fosters growth in technical, communication, teamwork and leadership skills.

Educational standards and criteria for construction education are established by the American Council for Construction Education (ACCE) which is the accrediting agency for construction education programs at all levels. The program at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln, having met these standards and criteria, is currently fully accredited by ACCE.

MAJOR DEPARTMENT ADMISSION

Students must complete 28 semester hours or be classified as a sophomore before applying for admission to the construction management degree program.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Requirements for the Degree (Lincoln Campus)

First Semester

CNST 131 Introduction to the Construction Industry 1

ENGR 10 Freshman Engineering Seminar 0

ENGL 151 Writing & Argument 3

GEOL 101 Physical Geology 4

MATH 106 Calculus I 5

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisified ACE outcomes 5, 7, or 9.

Total 16

Second Semester

CNST 112 Construction Communications 3

JGEN 200 Technical Communication I 3

STAT 218 Introduction to Statistics 3

PHYS 151 Elements of Physics 4

PHYS 153 Elements of Physics Lab 1

Total 14

Third Semester

CIVE 221 Geometric Control Systems 3

CNST 241 Construction Methods & Equipment I 3

CNST 252 Construction Materials & Testing 3

CNST 251 Construction Materials & Specifications 3

ENGR 20 Sophomore Engineering Seminar 0

CNST 225 Introduction to Building Information Modeling 3

Total 15

Fourth Semester

ACCT 200 Accounting for Business Decisions 3

CNST 242 Construction Equipment & Methods II 3

ECON 200 Economic Essentials & Issues 3

COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 7, or 9.

Total 15

Fifth Semester

ARCH 331 Structural Mechanics 3

CNST 344 Construction Site Safety Management 3

CNST 305 Building Environmental Technical Systems I 3

CNST 378 Construction Estimating 3

MNGT 300 Management Essentials for Contemporary Organizations 3

Total 15

Sixth Semester

ARCH 332 Structural Optimization 3

CNST 306 Building Environmental Technical Systems II 3

CNST 379 Construction Estimating II 3

BLAW 300 Business, Government & Society 3

FINA 300 Financial Decision Making 3

Total 15

Seventh Semester

CNST 476 Project Budgets & Controls 3

CNST 420 Professional Practice & Ethics 3

CNST 485 Construction Planning, Scheduling & Controls 3

MRKT 300 Contemporary Marketing 3

Technical/Design Elective 3

Total 15

Eighth Semester

CNST 480 Productivity & Human Factors in Construction 3

CNST 489 Senior Construction Project 3

Construction Management Elective 3

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course from not yet satisfied ACE outcomes 5, 7, or 9.

Technical/Design Elective 3

Total 15

Total Credit Hours Required for Graduation 120

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Construction management students must pass all courses offered within the College of Engineering and all math and science courses with a grade of “C” or higher.

ACE Requirements

The CNST program follows the UNL ACE general education requirements. Because of the specific needs of the program, most of these courses are specified in the curriculum. Please contact Melissa Hoffman at melissa.hoffman@unl.edu or 402-554-4482, if you are interested in more information about this program.

Exit Examination

Senior students will be asked to participate in a program exit examination. There will be an opportunity to participate in the American Institute of Constructors' Level I examination before graduation.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

This minor is for Engineering and Architecture majors ONLY.

The College of Engineering enables its students to participate in this approved minor subject to the following conditions:

1. A minor will not reduce or alter the existing course or degree requirements for students electing to pursue a minor.

2. A student’s minor program must be organized and approved by an advisor prior to the submission of the senior check to the department chair or head.

3. The minor must be approved by the advisor, the department chair or head, the Dean and the cognizant program offering the minor.

4. The College of Engineering will follow the “Plan A/B” format of the Arts and Sciences College in which a student pursuing a single minor must complete the “Plan A” requirements. A student pursuing a double (or greater) minor must fulfill either the “Plan A” or “Plan B” requirements for both minors depending on which plan is offered by the cognizant department.

5. Minors on the Lincoln or Omaha campuses may be added by approval of the College of Engineering Curriculum Committee and faculty.

Course Requirements

Plan A only

All courses must be taken for a letter grade.

Required Courses 27

BLAW 300 Business, Government & Society 3

CNST 112 Construction Communications 3

CNST 241 Construction Methods & Equipment I 3

CNST 305 Building Environmental Technical Systems I (ARCH 333) 3

CNST 378 Construction Estimating I (CONE 378) 3

CNST 379 Construction Estimating II 3

CNST 480 Productivity & Human Factors in Construction 3

CNST 485 Construction Planning, Scheduling & Controls (CONE 485) 3

MNGT 300 Management Essentials for Contemporary Organizations 3

Early Childhood Education in a Mobile Society

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Early Childhood Education in a Mobile Society

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

ADVISOR: Valerie Wiemeyer

DESCRIPTION

Early Childhood Education in a Mobile Society (ECEMS) will prepare you to work in early childhood settings with young children whose family members are highly mobile. When you complete the program, you will be qualified to work in a variety of programs that offer early care and education for children birth to age 8 and particularly those with highly mobile populations such as military installations.

This is an online program offered as part of the Great Plains Interactive Distance Education Alliance (IDEA). The Great Plains IDEA is a consortium of universities collaborating in the delivery of programs. As a student in this program, you will enroll for all your course work through UNL and you will graduate from UNL, but your online courses will be taught by faculty at each of the participating universities. Core courses (45 credits; identified under the heading ECEMS Requirements below) in this program are subject to differential tuition at the common Great Plains IDEA rate. For 2016-2017, this rate is $390 per credit hour. The Great Plains IDEA rate does not apply to tuition and fees for any remaining credit hours needed to complete the bachelors degree (i.e., ACE requirements, minor and elective requirements).

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Endorsement Requirements

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 33

ACE 1. Any ACE 1 Course (Suggested online courses: ENGL 151) 3

ACE 2. Any ACE 2 Course (Suggested online course: COMM 286) 3

ACE 3. Any ACE 3 Course (Suggested online courses: CSCE 101, ECON 215, MATH 104) 3

ACE 4. Any ACE 4 Course (Suggested online courses: AGRI 115, AGRO 131, ENTO 115) 3

ACE 5. Any ACE 5 Course (Suggested online courses: GPSP 377, NRES 130) 3

ACE 6. Any ACE 6 Course (Suggested online courses: ANTH 110, CRIM 101, ECON 211, SOCI 209, SOCI 225) 3

ACE 7. Any ACE 7 Course (Suggested online courses: AHIS 101) 3

ACE 8. Any ACE 8 Course (Suggested online courses: CYAF 150, ECON 211) 3

ACE 9. Any ACE 9 Course (Suggested online courses: ANTH 110, ECON 321, GPSP 377, GPSP 378, POLS 160, SOCI 200, SOCI 225, WMNS 101, WMNS 377) 3

ACE 10. CYAF 410 (ECEMS Requirement) 6

ECEMS Requirements 45

NOTE: Students must be admitted into the ECEMS program to take these courses. Admission requirements: 30 credit hours completed, 2.5 cumulative GPA.

CYAF 203, CYAF 204, CYAF 205, CYAF 301, CYAF 302, CYAF 303, CYAF 304, CYAF 305, CYAF 306, CYAF 307, CYAF 405, CYAF 406, CYAF 407, CYAF 408, CYAF 409, 3 hrs each;

CYAF 410 6 hrs (6 hrs met in ACE 10 )

Electives/Minor: 42

Total Hours 120

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for CYAF courses.

Pass/No Pass Limits

All CYAF courses must be taken for a grade (not Pass/No Pass).

OTHER

Criminal History Background Check

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS) has the responsibility to ensure that all students who interact with children of all ages, served by schools or other public or private agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior. These CEHS students must complete an official criminal history background check through the CEHS vendor, prior to participating in a field experience or internship. Students are responsible for the cost of any required criminal history background check and will be required to complete one upon admission to a program and/or an initial field placement. Eighteen months after the initial background check has been completed, undergraduate students are required to complete the CEHS self-disclosure report, a self-report collected by the college. Graduate students will be required to complete the self-disclosure report at the same time as the initial background check is conducted and again eighteen months later. If more than three years have elapsed after the initial background check is conduced, CEHS students must complete an additional background check prior to participating in a field experience or internship. Students are responsible for the cost of additional background checks.

Students with felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, as reported on the background check, may be contacted by the College. Depending upon the frequency and severity of the charges and/or convictions, students may be required to meet with the Director of Professional Experiences. If any new charges or convictions are acquired after a background check has been completed, students are required to report those to the Director of Professional Experiences within two weeks after the event occurs. Failure to disclose any new information concerning one's criminal history can lead to removal from the program. Continued participation in school or community field experiences in the College will be based on the type and number of convictions, the recency of those occurrences, and whether they violate the requirements of the Nebraska Department of Education and/or the Nebraska Department of Health and Human Services. If the convictions are deemed to be serious in nature, a student may be prohibited from participating in a field experience in a pre-school, school or public agency setting. The student may then be referred to the department chair for further disciplinary action.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

Students planning to enter professions in education or the human sciences must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and others. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences requires that its students show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act in a responsible manner. Students must consider how the College, the profession, an employer, or the community perceive or evaluate the impact of any questionable behavior. Students' success in their profession is impaired by taking risks that are unacceptable for children, demonstrating a lack of professionalism and good judgment, and showing disregard for one's personal reputation or the integrity of the College.

The College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to evaluate student fitness for the profession and deny entry to or dismiss a student from any program if, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Professional Experiences, the College determines that the student's behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or represents risk to young persons. Such behaviors shall be adequate foundation to deny the student's participation in any practicum or field experience to protect the interests and safety of children. The consequences of unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will depend upon the unique circumstances involved.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Professional Experiences with respect to a criminal behavior or unprofessional behavior, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing, within ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student's written appeal shall clearly explain the basis for the appeal. The Dean will review the student's basis for appeal and is authorized but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student's written appeal. The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possible, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Professional Experiences a written decision, which shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review with the University of Nebraska.

Engineering Leadership Minor

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Engineering Leadership Minor

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 18

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR: Carmen Zafft

DESCRIPTION

Chair and Advisor:

Faculty:

Overview and Purpose

The engineering leadership minor provides students an opportunity to focus on building leadership, management, and interpersonal skills needed to solve many of our societal challenges. Students complete a series of leadership, project management and interpersonal skills courses using experiential learning strategies and combine subject area knowledge gained in courses from their majors with strategies and skills to effectively lead in the engineering profession.

Courses included in the minor are leadership courses developed for the minor and focus on leadership, management and interpersonal skill needs of engineering students as well as courses lead by the faculty in the Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication.

This minor is intended to serve students in the College of Engineering. The minor contributes to the National Academy of Engineers call to expose engineering students to formal studies of leadership development (NAE, 2004) and the College of Engineering's mission to graduate the "Complete Engineer."

MAJOR DEPARTMENT ADMISSION

Open to student in the College of Engineering only.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

The engineering leadership minor is an interdisciplinary program; providing course offerings through the College of Engineering (COE) and the Department of Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication (ALEC). To successfully complete the minor, students are required to complete 18 credit hours in leadership and professional development; 9 of which come from engineering leadership and management courses.

Courses

ENGR Leadership & Management Courses 9

ENGR 100 Interpersonal Skills for Engineering Leaders (ACE 2) 3

ENGR 200 Professionalism & Global Perspective (ACE 6 & 9) 3

ENGR 320 Leadership, Management & Ethics (ACE 6 & 8) 3

Leadership Courses 3-6

Select one or two theory-based courses from the following: 3-6

ALEC 202 Foundations of Leadership Theory & Practice (3 cr)

ALEC 302 Dynamics of Effective Leadership in Organizations (3 cr)

*ALEC 433 Dynamics of Effective Leadership in Groups & Teams (3 cr)

ALEC 477 Leadership & Motivation (3 cr)

Select one or two application courses from the following: 3-6

ALEC 407 Supervisory Leadership (3 cr)

*ALEC 410 Environmental Leadership (3 cr)

*ALEC 422 Facilitation & Project Planning (3 cr)

*ALEC 466 Leadership & Diversity in Organizations & Communities (3 cr)

Experiential Learning in Leadership 0-3

Select zero to one course from the following:

**ALEC 337 Instructional Internship in Leadership Development (3 cr)

Total 18

* Note that junior standing is required for these courses.

** Credit received for being an undergraduate teaching assistant at the selection of the instructor.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

All courses must be completed with a Pass, or grade of C or higher.

Up to 6 credit hours may be taken as Pass/No Pass.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Requirement 1

English

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: English

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR: Kelly Payne

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Marco Abel

Vice Chair: Stephen Buhler

Professors: Abel, Agee, Bauer, Behrendt, Brooke, Buhler, Castro, Dawes, Dixon, Foster, Garelick, Goodburn, Homestead, Honey, Kaye, Kooser, Lynch, Price, Reynolds, Stenberg, White

Associate Professors: Capuano, Dreher, Gailey, Gannon, Jockers, Minter, Montes, Ramsay, Rutledge, Schaffert, Schleck, Végső

Assistant Professors: Capó Crucet, Obioma, Stage, Waite, Wendler, Wisnicki

Research Associate Professor: Ronning

Research Assistant Professor: Rilett

Associate Professor of Practice: Griffin

Assistant Professors of Practice: Azima, Vespa

The Department of English seeks to provide for the diverse needs of its students by offering them the opportunity to read widely, to understand and enjoy what they read, and to express themselves both orally and in writing with ease, force and clarity. Through the practice of writing and the study of language, literature and film, the department strives to stimulate humanistic learning and the capacity to respond rationally and imaginatively to literature and the life it reflects.

The undergraduate major in English is designed for three groups: 1) those who seek a general education; 2) those who plan to teach in the elementary and secondary schools; and 3) those who plan to pursue graduate study in the field. The major is also frequently chosen as preparation for professional study in law, medicine, and business, and for careers in other fields such as publishing, editing, library science, and digital humanities. Many students find the English major is a fine complement to a major in a professional field.

A student declaring an English major will meet with the advisor to establish a plan for the major. Thereafter the student must meet with the advisor at least once a year to update the major plan, review progress toward the degree, plan a concentration, and consult about course selection, scholarships, and careers or post-graduate education. The department Advising Center (201 Andrews Hall) will offer written information about these matters and others of interest to majors.

Special Programs. The Department of English houses the major in Film Studies and participates in the majors in Ethnic Studies, Environmental Studies, and in Womens and Gender Studies; in the minors in African American Studies, U.S. Latina/Latino Studies, Ethnic Studies, Native American Studies, Jewish Studies, Medieval and Renaissance Studies, Environmental Studies, Religious Studies, and Digital Humanities.

The Curriculum

Course Offerings. English courses are regularly offered in drama, poetry, and fiction; the English language; periods and authors in British and American literature; women's and minority literatures; creative and expository writing; literary and rhetorical theory and criticism; digital humanities; and film. For the precise courses offered or to be offered in any particular semester, see the Office of the University Registrar's website at registrar.unl.edu for that semester. A course description booklet is also available in the departmental office and online before each early registration period.

Credit Hours. Undergraduate English courses will usually yield 3 semester hours of credit. Graduate-level seminars are usually offered for variable credit (normally 3 or 4 credit hours). The letter suffix H indicates an honors course.

Independent Study. This course of study is a provision for students wishing to study areas of literature and language not covered or insufficiently covered in regularly scheduled classes. Students must secure permission from a professorial staff member willing to direct their study and must file an Independent Directed Reading Contract (available in the Advising Center, 201 Andrews Hall) with the Undergraduate Advisor.

NOTE: Neither ENGL 495 (Internship) nor ENGL 497 (Independent Study) count towards fulfilling 400-level requirements for majors and minors. A maximum of 6 credit hours of ENGL 399 (Independent Study) and/or ENGL 497 may count towards the 300-level requirement for the major.

Prerequisites. The first course in English is ordinarily chosen from courses numbered 100-151. However, international students who are not native speakers of English normally take English courses such as ENGL 140, ENGL 141, ENGL 142, ENGL 186, ENGL 187, and ENGL 188.

Course Levels

100 Level. Introductory courses are open only to freshman and sophomore students. Transfer students and others who have not met the communication requirement and are juniors or seniors must choose ENGL 254 or ENGL 354 to complete this requirement. (In unusual cases, exceptions to this rule may be granted by the Advisor, English Department.) Writing is emphasized in courses numbered 100-199, and all such courses except ENGL 140, ENGL 141, ENGL 142, ENGL 180, ENGL 189H, ENGL 186, and ENGL 187, are designed to fulfill ACE Outcome 1. Newly admitted students who are not native speakers of English must take an English placement examination to determine their appropriate course requirement.

200 Level. Courses designed for the intermediate student who has completed or is concurrently taking one or two courses in English.

300 Level. Courses designed for the intermediate student who ordinarily will have had two courses at the 200 level. These students should normally take the remainder of their courses at the 300 level or 400 level. English majors and minors should advance to the 300 level as soon as possible.

400 Level. Courses designed for the advanced student or the student with a special interest. English majors must take at least 6 credit hours at the 400 level.

800/900 Level. Graduate courses. Graduate standing and at least 18 hours of undergraduate course work in English are prerequisite to courses at the 800- and 900-level. Advanced undergraduates may register in 800- and 900-level courses with the permission of the Dean of Graduate Studies, provided that these hours do not count towards their baccalaureate requirements.

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy are offered. For details see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

39 hours with a minimum of 18 credit hours at the 300 level and above, 6 hours of which must be at the 400 level.

The major also requires a minimum number of these 39 hours in different areas or courses:

A. ENGL 200 (3)

B. Writing (3)

ENGL 251, ENGL 252, ENGL 253, ENGL 254, ENGL 354, or ENGL 454

C. Theory (3)

ENGL 270, ENGL 275, ENGL 373, ENGL 375, ENGL 376, ENGL 457A, ENGL 475, ENGL 475A, ENGL 478, or ENGL 480

D. Historical Contexts (9)

At least 3 credits must be in a pre-1800 literature, noted with an asterisk

Historical Surveys (3)

One of the following: ENGL 230*, ENGL 231, ENGL 260*, ENGL 261

Historical Focus: (6)

One course from each of the following categories

Early Literatures

ENGL 244E*, ENGL 305A, ENGL 311, ENGL 330*, ENGL 330E*, ENGL 332, ENGL 362*, ENGL 363*, ENGL 364*

Recent Literatures

ENGL 205, ENGL 244, ENGL 301B, ENGL 302, ENGL 302A, ENGL 331, ENGL 333, ENGL 365, ENGL 405E

E. Diversity and Global Awareness (6)

At least 3 credits must be in an Ethnic Studies course, noted with asterisk

ENGL 212, ENGL 215, ENGL 243, ENGL 244*, ENGL 244A*, ENGL 244E*, ENGL 245A*, ENGL 245J, ENGL 245N*, ENGL 315A, ENGL 315B, ENGL 317, ENGL 344*, ENGL 344B*, ENGL 344D*, ENGL 345D*, ENGL 345N*, ENGL 349

F. Capstone Course (3)

ENGL 487

G. Concentration or electives (12)

(12 hours at the 300- or 400- level)

TOTAL CREDITS 39

Note: A single course may only be applied to one category.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required from time to time to complete written exit surveys and to compile portfolios of selected written work in major courses. All such work will be assessed in ways that assure student anonymity.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

Concentrations or electives. Students interested in particular areas of study, with particular career goals, or who desire to attend graduate school, should consider developing a concentration to support those interests or aspirations. Students select four courses at the 300 or 400 level that concentrate on a particular area of study.. Students may choose one of the department's recommended areas of concentration, or they may design their own concentration in consultation with the advisor and appropriate faculty members. Recommended areas of concentration include:

Creative writing

Composition and Rhetoric

Digital Humanities

Environmental and Place studies

Ethnic studies

Editing and Publishing

Film studies

Literary & Critical Theory

Medieval and Renaissance studies

Women's and Gender studies

19th Century studies

In some cases, an interdisciplinary concentration may include a course from another department. Students wishing to develop a concentration are encouraged to consult with the English Undergraduate Advising Office (201 Andrews) early in their program.

Students who do not wish to pursue a concentration may choose any four 300 or 400 level courses as electives.

Career Preparation

The English department is committed to preparing majors for the job market. We strongly encourage all majors to enroll in ENGL 300 Professional Practices for English Majors during their sophomore or junior year, and to consider taking advantage of UCARE, internships, educational abroad, volunteering and other career development opportunities.

Minor Requirements

English majors are required to complete one Plan A minor or two Plan B minors or a second major.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

A student may apply up to 6 hours of Pass/No Pass credit toward a major in English without securing permission; and a student may apply up to 3 hours of Pass/No Pass credit toward a minor in English, subject to the approval of the department granting the major. To secure the necessary approval, students may obtain request forms from the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

No more than 6 Pass/No Pass hours can count for the English major. No course can count for more than one requirement.

Course Level Requirement

No more than 6 hours of Independent Directed Reading (including internships) will count for the major. Neither independent study taken at the 400 level (ENGL 497) nor an internship (ENGL 495) will count for the 400-level requirement for the major. Students taking 6 hours of ENGL 399H may count for the major no more than 3 additional hours of Independent Directed Reading. No more than 3 hours of internship (ENGL 495) will count for the English major.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A. 18 hrs of English at the 200 level and above; 9 hrs must be above 299; of these 9 hrs, 3 hrs must be above 399.

Plan B. 12 hrs of English at the 200 level and above; 6 hrs above 299.

No more than 3 hours of Pass/No Pass may count for a minor in English.

Entrepreneurship Minor

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Entrepreneurship Minor

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 12 or 18

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR:

DESCRIPTION

Faculty: Nelson, Titus, Waterson, Welbourne

The minor in Entrepreneurship is targeted toward students who might not traditionally interact with the College of Business Administration and the local entrepreneurial community. The goal of the minor is to teach non-CBA students how to create successful businesses based on the expertise developed in their majors. Two tracks will be offered: one for business majors that emphasizes core entrepreneurship courses; the other for non-business majors which covers basic business courses along with the entrepreneurship core. These tracks allow the student to tailor the minor to their needs according to the type of business they plan to pursue.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Program Structure

Students will enroll in one of two tracks:

Non-CBA Student Track – In addition to the core entrepreneurship curriculum, students on this track will take basic courses in finance, accounting, and marketing. This track is intended for students unfamiliar with the foundational business practices.

CBA Student Track – Students taking this track will complete the core entrepreneurship courses offered by the Center. This track is intended for students majoring in fields housed within CBA.

Core Courses

Non-CBA Student Track (9 hours Entrepreneurship + 9 hours Business for non-majors)

ENTR 321 - Introduction to Entrepreneurship and Innovation

ENTR 421 - Initiating and Managing Entrepreneurial Growth

ENTR 423 - Business Plan Development and Decision Making

ACCT 200 - Accounting for Business Decisions

MRKT 300 - Contemporary Marketing or ECON 200 - Economic Essentials and Issues

FINA 300 - Financial Decision Making

CBA-Student Track (12 hours Entrepreneurship)

ENTR 321 - Introduction to Entrepreneurship and Innovation

ENTR 421 - Initiating and Managing Entrepreneurial Growth

ENTR 422 - Managing Rapid Growth and Change

ENTR 423 - Business Plan Development and Decision Making

Credits earned using the Pass/No Pass option do not count towards this minor.

Family Science

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Family Science

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE:

ADVISOR: Judy Hofeldt

DESCRIPTION

Human Development and Family Science provides a comprehensive program grounded in family science theory, research, and professional practice and application for individuals to work with children and families. This career path provides students with knowledge and intervention skills that will assist them in helping to prevent and remedy interpersonal problems experienced by individuals in their family relationships, building on the family’s strengths. In addition, Human Development and Family Science will prepare students for graduate school (e.g. family science, family therapy, social work, counseling psychology, and law), or for employment in human services agencies or programs.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Program Requirements

Degree at a Glance

ACE Requirements 30-43

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. ALEC 102, COMM 210, COMM 283, COMM 286 (Supporting Courses) 3

ACE 3. ECON 215, EDPS 459, MATH 104, MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 203, MATH 208, STAT 218 (Supporting Courses) 3-5

ACE 4. ANTH 242 & ANTH 242L, CHEM 105, CHEM 109, CHEM 110, CHEM 113, ENTO 115 & ENTO 116, GEOG 155, GEOL 101, GEOL 103, LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L, LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L, METR 100, NRES 108, PHYS 141, PHYS 142, PHYS 151 & PHYS 153, PHYS 260 & PHYS 262, TMFD 206 (Supporting Courses) 3-5

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. CYAF 160 (CYAF Core Requirements) 3

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. 3

ACE 9. CYAF 495A or other ACE 9 course (CYAF Core Requirements) 3

ACE 10. CYAF 497D, 3 hrs (CYAF Core Req.) or CYAF 497A, 12 hrs (Child Serv. Track) 3-12

CYAF Core Requirements 24

CYAF 222, CYAF 280, CYAF 285, CYAF 382, (CYAF 446 or CYAF 458), CYAF 460, CYAF 471, CYAF 488 (3 hr ea)

Choose one of the following Tracks: 9-18

Approved Minor Track 18

Choose from: Anthropology, communication studies, education, gerontology, global studies, leadership and communications, psychology or sociology

Research Track (recommended for interest in graduate studies) 9-13

NOTE: A cumulative 3.5 GPA is required for this track.

CYAF 498 3-6

Choose two from: PSYC 350 (4 hr), PSYC 450, EDPS 459, SOCI 205, SOCI 206 (3 hr ea) 6-7

Child Services Track (recommended for interest in child studies) 18

CYAF 270 & CYAF 270L, CYAF 271 & CYAF 271L, CYAF 371 & CYAF 371L, CYAF 458, CYAF 474, SPED 201 (3 hr ea)

Electives 35-57

Total Hours 120

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within an education endorsement program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their advisor prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students’ academic program.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR/ENDORSEMENT REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for CYAF courses. This also applies to any courses used as substitutions for CYAF courses.

Pass/No Pass Limits

All CYAF courses, and any substitutions for CYAF courses, must be taken for a grade (not Pass/No Pass).

OTHER

Criminal History Background Check Requirement

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS) has the responsibility to ensure that all students who interact with children of all ages, served by schools or other public or private agencies meet a high level of personal, professional and ethical behavior. These CEHS students must complete an official criminal history background check through the CEHS vendor, prior to participating in a field experience or internship. Students are responsible for the cost of any required criminal history background check and will be required to complete one upon admission to a program and/or an initial field placement. Eighteen months after the initial background check has been completed, undergraduate students are required to complete the CEHS self-disclosure report, a self-report collected by the college. Graduate students will be required to complete the self-disclosure report at the same time as the initial background check is conducted and again eighteen months later. If more than three years have elapsed after the initial background check is conduced, CEHS students must complete an additional background check prior to participating in a field experience or internship. Students are responsible for the cost of additional background checks.

Students with felony or any misdemeanor charges or convictions, as reported on the background check, may be contacted by the College. Depending upon the frequency and severity of the charges and/or convictions, students may be required to meet with the Director of Professional Experiences. If any new charges or convictions are acquired after a background check has been completed, students are required to report those to the Director of Professional Experiences within two weeks after the event occurs. Failure to disclose any new information concerning one's criminal history can lead to removal from the program. Continued participation in school or community field experiences in the College will be based on the type and number of convictions, the recency of those occurrences, and whether they violate the requirements of the Nebraska Department of Education and/or the Nebraska Department of Health and Human Services. If the convictions are deemed to be serious in nature, a student may be prohibited from participating in a field experience in a pre-school, school or public agency setting. The student may then be referred to the department chair for further disciplinary action.

Professional and Ethical Behavior: Avoiding Risky Behaviors

Students planning to enter professions in education or the human sciences must be able to demonstrate that they are individuals of strong moral character who can make mature decisions for themselves and others. Therefore, the College of Education and Human Sciences requires that its students show a high degree of moral character and the ability to act in a responsible manner. Students must consider how the College, the profession, an employer, or the community perceive or evaluate the impact of any questionable behavior. Students' success in their profession is impaired by taking risks that are unacceptable for children, demonstrating a lack of professionalism and good judgment, and showing disregard for one's personal reputation or the integrity of the College.

The College of Education and Human Sciences reserves the right to evaluate student fitness for the profession and deny entry to or dismiss a student from any program if, through the reasonable exercise of the judgment of its Certification Officer or the Director of Professional Experiences, the College determines that the student's behavior represents a lack of integrity, questionable moral/ethical character, or represents risk to young persons. Such behaviors shall be adequate foundation to deny the student's participation in any practicum or field experience to protect the interests and safety of children. The consequences of unprofessional, unethical or risky behavior will depend upon the unique circumstances involved.

Appeal to the Dean

Should a student object to the determination made by the Certification Officer or the Director of Professional Experiences with respect to a criminal behavior or unprofessional behavior, the student may appeal to the Dean of the College, in writing, within ten days of the determination, requesting the Dean of the College to investigate and review the determination. The student's written appeal shall clearly explain the basis for the appeal. The Dean will review the student's basis for appeal and is authorized but not required to look into related concerns, whether or not sure concerns are contained in the student's written appeal. The Dean shall render a decision on the appeal as soon as reasonably possible, but in no case longer than 20 days following the initiation of the appeal. Once the Dean has completed the review and investigation, he or she shall deliver to the student and the Certification Officer or the Director of Professional Experiences a written decision, which shall be final and not subject to further appeal or review with the University of Nebraska.

General (CASNR)

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: General (CASNR)

DEGREE OFFERED: Non-degree seeking only

HOURS REQUIRED:

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE:

ADVISOR: Tiffany Heng-Moss

DESCRIPTION

Coordinator: Tiffany Heng-Moss, 103 Agricultural Hall

Many students are unsure of which degree program to choose when entering the university. In fact, over half of all students entering UNL change their degree program at least once. The following program is available for students not yet ready to make the decision.

Exploratory Studies

The courses listed below compose a non-degree program entitled Exploratory Studies. The program is designed for students who are interested in a bachelor of science degree in the applied life sciences, agricultural sciences, natural resource sciences, or social sciences offered in the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources, but are uncertain about a specific degree program. Such students will receive individualized advising and mentoring from a faculty member and be encouraged to participate in clubs and other pre-professional activities to help them decide which career path is right for them.

This list of suggested courses for the first semester should provide the student maximum flexibility while ensuring that courses contribute to any of the degree programs within the College as well as most programs in other colleges. During the first semester, students should contact Associate Dean Tiffany Heng-Moss to identify an appropriate advisor(s) in a degree program(s) of their area of interest to plan appropriate courses for subsequent semesters. Students may be in the program for two years (60 credit hours). Students may declare a degree program at any time, but must declare a degree program at the completion of 60 hours.

First Semester

ENGL 150 or ENGL 151 3

AGRI 103 Introduction to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems (NRES 103) 3

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab or LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I & Lab 4

MATH 102, MATH 104 or MATH 106 2-5

Comprehensive elective 3

Total 15

To learn about a particular degree program, please contact the CASNR Dean's Office at 402-472-2201.

Global Leadership Minor

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Global Leadership Minor

DEGREE OFFERED: Minor only

HOURS REQUIRED: 12

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA:

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR: John Osiri

DESCRIPTION

Chair and Advisor:

Faculty: Ibrayeva (management), Osiri (international programs)

The global leadership minor from the College of Business Administration (CBA) prepares students to be able to identify global opportunities to create, expand, or re-energize organizations and initiatives. The global issues course exposes students to human conditions and problems related to development, entrepreneurship, environment, population, and poverty. The leadership in a global context course focuses on international management from a U.S. perspective, and global leadership and the culture map is an experiential course where students learn how to launch an international venture or project while developing cultural competency. The project is interdisciplinary and may draw from education, engineering, science, social science, and humanities and is set in a particular cultural context. In addition to taking all three aforementioned courses, students are required to earn 3 credit hours while studying abroad on a CBA-approved program. The study abroad trip will provide students excellent global immersion experience and first-hand cultural context in a country of their choice. The minor is available to both business and nonbusiness students.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Requirements 12

BSAD 320 Global Issues 3

(Development, population, poverty, and entrepreneurship issues.)

MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context 3

BSAD 420 Global Leadership & the Culture Map 3

(Strategies and structures of multinational companies and in-depth focus on cross-cultural dimensions among countries. Taught from an international perspective, not taught from the perspective of U.S. enterprises. Additionally, students will work in teams to propose an international company expansion or launch an international venture.)

BSAD 491, ECON 466 or ECON 467 3

(Credit associated with a study abroad experience, or similar study abroad credit.)

By completing the 12 credit hours above, a UNL student can earn our global leadership minor. The minor is available to CBA and non-CBA UNL students. All courses will be offered online.

International Business

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: International Business

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (27-35 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No - See Global Leadership

ADVISOR: John Osiri

DESCRIPTION

Students in international business study the business practices of other nations and learn how international trade laws affect the world economy. A background in international business will help students become a better member of the management team of any corporation. From banks to manufacturing firms, an increasing number of industries need professionals who understand the world’s business environment. Import and export firms, agricultural commodities firms, and government and non-government agencies may specifically seek international expertise. It is suggested that students begin thinking about where they want to study abroad and their language and culture courses during the freshman year. Upper-level course work and education abroad experience will be done sometime in the junior or senior year.

Because the nature of the major requires studying abroad and careful selection of course work to complement and count for appropriate requirements, students are strongly encouraged to consult with their advisor or a staff member in the Undergraduate Programs Office.

In order for students to be successful in international business after graduation, they should plan to do the following as part of their university experience:

Internships related to international business
Involvement with international student groups
Language study
Courses that will provide them with greater awareness and knowledge of global issues
Education abroad experiences

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 27-35 hours of course work for the major. The broad components of an International Business major are:

1. Complete 15 credit hours of business courses selected from one of the following specialization Options:

Economics
Management
Finance
Marketing
Supply Chain Management
General International Business

2. Complete 12 hours of international business courses from the specified list for the selected specialization Option.
3. Fulfill a global immersion requirement by completing a study abroad experience and the equivalent of at least 8 credit hours of foreign language, which may be completed during the study abroad experience. It is possible that the language course work can be counted towards electives or left untranscripted.
4. Participate in an international internship/practicum experience.

As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade. No course work for this major may be double counted with any other business major or minor.

Specific Major Requirements

A. Specialization Options: To gain expertise in a functional area of business, IB majors must choose one specialization Option, and must complete the required courses for that Option. Required courses for each specialization Option are shown below.

B. International Business Courses: IB majors must take at least 12 credit hours from the IB course list associated with the selected specialization Option, including a required 3 credit hour integrated IB course (BSAD 398 Global Leadership and the Culture Map, described below). Up to 6 credits of BSAD 491 may be applied to the International Business Courses requirement. Students with interests in specific regions or countries should consider pursuing a regionally-focused minor (e.g. minor in African Studies or Asian Studies) and/or take BSAD 491 courses that focus in their region of interest (e.g. BSAD 491 - Doing Business in China)

C. BSAD 398 (Global Leadership and the Culture Map) is required for IB majors. This course will connect functional areas to global contexts. The course will cover international management from a strategic perspective with an in-depth focus on cross-cultural dimensions among countries. This course is taught from an international perspective, not taught from the perspective of US enterprises.

D. IB students are required to complete a global immersion experience comprised of a semester abroad. One semester abroad must be at least 13 weeks. This requirement may be met by two shorter study abroad experiences totaling 13 weeks.

E. Students must earn the equivalent of a minimum of 8 credit hours of foreign language credit. For many CBA-sponsored study abroad options, foreign language classes will be taught in the host country and the cost of the foreign language courses will be included in the study abroad program costs. Alternately, a student can complete a minimum of 8 credit hours of foreign language at UNL. International students are not allowed to use their native language to meet the foreign language requirement. International students may use English as their foreign language if English is not their native language by taking an equivalent of 8 credit hours of English language beyond their required English language courses. This additional language training must be aimed at improving written and/or spoken English proficiency. As such, the equivalencies may be a combination of credit or non-credit bearing courses, ESL courses, certificate programs, and/or structured conversational courses and programs. Equivalencies will be determined by assigning 1 credit hour to every 15 hours of language training. Training may be undertaken either at UNL or at a different institution, but should be pre-approved by the IB Director whose office will maintain a list of suggested courses and programs.

F. IB students are required to complete an international internship and/or practicum experience, which may be a paid or non-paid project-based practicum or traditional internship, and must be approved by the IB director. Students may take the initiative in arranging the internship or seek help through the IB program office or the CBA Career Services.

Tracks/Options/Concentrations/Emphases Requirements

IB majors must declare one of these specializations as a formal Option within their major. Specialization Options are available in economics, management, finance, marketing, supply chain management, and general international business. Specific requirements foreach specialization Option and the associated international business courses are shown below.

I. IB with Economics as a specialization Option

ECON 311 Intermediate Macroeconomics
ECON 312 Intermediate Microeconomics
ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics
+ECON 421 International Trade
+ECON 422 International Financ

International Business Courses:

Required Course:

BSAD 398 (Global Leadership and the Culture Map)
Select 9 credit hours from the following courses:
*MRKT 453 International Marketing
*SCMS 439 Global Sourcing and Distribution
MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Contex
SCMS 459 Global Information Systems
FINA 450 International Financial Management
+ECON 423 Economics of Less Developed Countriea
BSAD 398 (Global Issues)
BSAD 491 International Studies in Business and Economics

*indicates a course requires a prerequisite that is not in the business core (BCI) or the IB program of study

+indicates a course that is not offered every year

II. IB with Management as a specialization Option

MNGT 360 Organizational Behavior
MNGT/ENTR 321 Entrepreneurship and Innovation in Organizations
MNGT 361 Human Resource Management
MNGT 365 Diversity in Organizations
MNGT 412 Negotiating and Conflict Management

International Business Courses:

Required Course:

BSAD 398 (Global Leadership and the Culture Map)
Select 9 credit hours from the following courses:
*MRKT 453 International Marketing
*SCMS 439 Global Sourcing and Distribution
MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context
SCMS 459 Global Information Systems
+ECON 422 International Finance
FINA 450 International Financial Management
ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics
*+ECON 421 International Trade
+ECON 423 Economics of Less Developed Countries
BSAD 398 (Global Issues)
BSAD 491 International Studies in Business and Economics

*indicates a course requires a prerequisite that is not in the business core (BCI) or the IB program of study

+indicates a course that is not offered every year

III. IB with Finance as a specialization Option

FINA 363 Investment Principles
FINA 365 Financial Institutions and Markets
FINA 367 Fixed Income Investments
FINA 450 International Financial Management
FINA 461 Advanced Finance

International Business Courses:

Required Course:

BSAD 398 (Global Leadership and the Culture Map)
Select 9 credit hours from the following courses:
* MRKT 453 International Marketing
*SCMS 439 Global Sourcing and Distribution
MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context
SCMS 459 Global Information Systems
+ECON 422 International Finance
ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics
*+ECON 421 International Trade
+ECON 423 Economics of Less Developed Countries
BSAD 398 (Global Issues)
BSAD 491 International Studies in Business and Economics

*indicates a course requires a prerequisite that is not in the business core (BCI) or the IB program of study
+indicates a course that is not offered every year

IV. IB with Marketing as a specialization Option

MRKT 345 Market Research
MRKT 346 Market Channels Management
MRKT 347 Marketing Communication Strategy
MRKT 453 International Marketing
MRKT 442 Marketing Management

International Business Courses:

Required Course:

BSAD 398 (Global Leadership and the Culture Map)
Select 9 credit hours from the following courses:
*SCMS 439 Global Sourcing and Distribution
MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context
SCMS 459 Global Information Systems
+ECON 422 International Finance
FINA 450 International Financial Management
ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics
*+ECON 421 International Trade
+ECON 423 Economics of Less Developed Countries
BSAD 398 (Global Issues)
BSAD 491 International Studies in Business and Economics

*indicates a course requires a prerequisite that is not in the business core (BCI) or the IB program of study

+indicates a course that is not offered every year

V. IB with Supply Chain Management as a specialization Option

SCMS 335 Supply Chain Decision Making Models
SCMS 431 Enterprise Management Systems
SCMS 432 Supply Chain Planning and Control Systems
SCMS 439 Global Sourcing and Distribution
SCMS/MRKT 346 Market Channels Management

International Business Courses:

Required Course:

BSAD 398 (Global Leadership and the Culture Map)
Select 9 credit hours from the following courses:
*MRKT 453 International Marketing
SCMS 459 Global Information Systems
+ECON 422 International Finance
FINA 450 International Financial Management
ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics
*+ECON 421 International Trade
+ECON 423 Economics of Less Developed Countries
MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context
BSAD 398 (Global Issues)
BSAD 491 International Studies in Business and Economics

*indicates a course requires a prerequisite that is not in the business core (BCI) or the IB program of study

+indicates a course that is not offered every year

VI. IB with General International Business as a specialization Option

ACCT 301 Using Accounting Information
ECON 311 Intermediate Microeconomics or ECON312 Intermediate Macroeconomics
FINA363 Investment Principles
MNGT360 Organizational Behavior
SCMS/MRKT 346 Market Channels Management

International Business Courses:

Required Course:

BSAD 398 (Global Leadership and the Culture Map)
Select 9 credit hours from the following courses:
*MRKT 453 International Marketing
*SCMS 439 Global Sourcing and Distribution
MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context

SCMS 459 Global Information Systems
+ECON 422 International Finance
*+ECON 421 International Trade
+ECON 423 Economics of Less Developed Countries

BSAD 398 (Global Issues)
BSAD 491 International Studies in Business and Economics

*indicates a course requires a prerequisite (in bold-face) that is not in the business core (BCI) or the IB program of study
+indicates a course that is not offered every year

Minor Requirements

While not required, students should consider a minor in language and/or consider options in other departments related to the country of interest (i.e., history, political science, global studies, Asian studies, ethnic or European studies, Latin American studies, etc.)

Refer to Arts and Science minors for options and requirements which may compliment the geographical area and/or language of interest.
Those interested in pursuing a language minor may be able to double count NBR 4–Ace 5. Students will need to compare the requirements for their minor with the ACE course list to determine applicability.
In any of these instances, credit hours count only ONCE; student still needs 120 hours for the degree.
Be sure to distinguish differences between Plan A & Plan B minors (as Plan A requires completion of only ONE minor, while Plan B requires completion of an additional minor).

Ace Courses for IB Majors

Students are advised to be strategic in taking their ACE courses. Take your courses to satisfy your general curiosity, to learn something about an area or a region where you want to or may do business, or to strengthen your global or functional strength.

ACE 4 – Science

Suggested courses that relates to current and future global business activities are:

ANTH 142 Basics of Biological Anthropology

ANTH 232 Introduction to Prehistory
ASTR 103 Descriptive Astronomy
ASTR 117 Life in Universe
GEOG 155 Elements of Physical Geography
GEOL 100 Introduction to Geology
GEOL 103 Historical Geology
GEOL 120 Geology of National Parks and Monuments
METR 180 Environment, Energy, and Climate Change
NRES 108 Earth's Natural Resource Systems Laboratory
GEOL 109 Oceanography
GEOL 115 The Earth’s Energy Resources
PHYS 260 Liberal Arts Physics: Matter and Motion
PHYS 261 Liberal Arts Physics: Atoms and Fields
POLS 250 Genetics, Brains, and Politics

For example, take ASTR 117 Life in the Universe to ponder upon how humans might work together to explore planets and “interplanetary” business; take ANTH 232 Introduction to prehistory to learn how cities arose around the world, and take POLS 250 Genetics, Brains, and Politics to strengthen a functional area in management.

ACE 5 - Humanities

Take any course that piques your mind, relates to a region of interest, or strengthens your functional area. For example, take ENGL/HIST 277 Being Human in a Digital Age to complement an interest in e-commerce or supply chain; take ENGL 311 Revolution and Romanticism, if you are interested in doing business in Italy, and take History of Design to strengthen a functional area in economics.

ACE 7 – Study of Arts

Take any course that piques your mind, relates to a region of interest, or strengthens your functional area. For example, take ENGL 170 Beginning Creative Writing to complement a business writing interest; take MUSIC 280 World Music to learn about the music cultures of parts of Asia, Africa, and Europe, and take ENGL 439 Film Directors to strengthen a functional area in management functional area.

ACE 9 – Human Diversity and Global Awareness

Several business international courses count for ACE 9 credit, or take any course that piques your mind, relates to a region of interest, or strengthens your functional area. For example, consider COMM 211 Intercultural Communication to complement a business communication interest; take ETHN 203 Introduction to Africa if you are interested in doing business in Africa, or take MNGT 365 Diversity in Organizations to better understand how to manage a diverse workforce.

Electives

See College Degree Requirements–Electives for additional options/restrictions regarding elective credit for the degree.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Enrollment in most upper-level business courses usually requires completion of an introductory course in that major area as well as other prerequisites. Refer to course descriptions EARLY in the program to plan for completion of specific course prerequisites.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

Course Level Requirement

Enrollment in language courses above the 101 level requires appropriate placement on the Modern Language Placement exam.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Students interested in a minor related to International Business should consider a minor in Global Leadership.

Microbiology (ASC)

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Microbiology (ASC)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE:

ADVISOR: James Alfano

DESCRIPTION

Director: Jim Alfano, Department of Plant Pathology and Center for Plant Science Innovation

Advisory Committee: Atkin, School of Biological Sciences; Blum, School of Biological Sciences; Buan, Dept. of Biochemistry; Hutkins, Dept. of Food Science and Technology; Moxley, School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences; Zhang, Nebraska Center for Virology and School of Biological Sciences

Academic Advisor: James Alfano

Website: http://microbiology.unl.edu

The microbiology major is an interdepartmental major that offers educational opportunities in various areas of microbiology leading to a bachelor of science degree in microbiology. The training offered is suitable for a professional career in microbiology, which may lead to employment in the food industry, clinical microbiology, biotechnology, and pharmaceuticals; or federal agencies such as the Food and Drug Administration, U.S. Department of Agriculture, U.S. Public Health Service, and Environmental Protection Agency. The program is also suitable as preparation for graduate studies leading to academic careers and professional careers in medicine, dentistry, veterinary medicine, pharmacy, and health-related fields. (Completion of the microbiology baccalaureate degree program does not automatically fulfill the admission requirements for application to a given professional program. Students considering application to a professional program are strongly encouraged to work with their advisor to ensure that admission requirements are met during completion of the microbiology degree.)

Students interested in majoring in microbiology are advised to make an appointment with the academic advisor.

Students concerned about their preparation for college-level biology should take LIFE 120 with an understanding that they will need to use the resource center and plan their time accordingly to allow for increased study time. Please consult your advisor if in doubt.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements (13-14 credit hours)

BIOS 312 Microbiology (3 cr)

BIOS 313 Molecular Microbiology Lab (2 cr) or BIOS 314 Microbiology Lab (1 cr)

MBIO 440 Microbial Physiology (BIOS 440) (3 cr)

MBIO 420 Molecular Genetics (BIOS 420) (3 cr)

MBIO 443 Immunology (BIOS 443) (3 cr)

Specific Major Requirements

Natural Sciences (38-42 credit hours)

NOTE: If you plan to take BIOC 431, it will increase your natural sciences hours by 3 credits and put you over the 42 credit hours for natural sciences. Adjustments may need to be made in other areas.

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I & Lab (4 cr)

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L Fundamentals of Biology II & Lab (4 cr)

BIOS 206 General Genetics (4 cr)

CHEM 109 & CHEM 110 General Chemistry I & II (8 cr) [or CHEM 113 & CHEM 114 Fundamental Chemistry I & II & CHEM 221 Elementary Quantitative Analysis (11 cr)]

If you plan to take BIOC 321 & BIOC 321L, select one sequence from:

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 Organic Chemistry I & Lab (4 cr)

CHEM 261 & CHEM 263 Organic Chemistry & Lab (5 cr)

CHEM 255 & CHEM 257 Biological Organic Chemistry & Lab (4 cr)

If you plan to take BIOC 431 (3 cr), select one sequence from:

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 Organic Chemistry I & Lab (4 cr) & CHEM 252 Organic Chemistry II (3 cr)

CHEM 261 & CHEM 263 Organic Chemistry & Lab (5 cr) & CHEM 262 Organic Chemistry (3 cr)

PHYS 141 & PHYS 142 Elementary General Physics I & II (10 cr) [or PHYS 211 & PHYS 221 General Physics I & Lab (5 cr) & PHYS 212 & PHYS 222 General Physics II & Lab (5 cr)]

BIOC 321 & BIOC 321L Elements of Biochemistry & Lab (4 cr) or BIOC 431 Structure and Metabolism (3 cr)

NOTE: BIOS 207 Ecology and Evolution is also recommended for students specializing in Applied, Environmental, and Plant Microbiology or who are interested in epidemiology.

Mathematics and Statistics (8 credit hours)

MATH 106 Calculus I (5 cr)

STAT 218 Introduction to Statistics (3 cr) (or one of EDPS 459, ECON 215, STAT 380)

Microbiology Electives

(12-18 credit hours, a minimum of 12 hours from the list below)

BIOC 432 Metabolism & Biological Information (3 cr)

BIOC 433 Biochemistry Lab (2 cr)

BIOC 437 Research Techniques in Biochemistry (BIOS 437) (4 cr)

BIOC 442 Computational Biology (STAT 442) (3 cr)

BIOS 302 Cell Biology (3 cr)

BIOS 303 Molecular Biology (3 cr)

BIOS 326 Biology of Viruses (3 cr)

BIOS 402 Cancer Biology (3 cr)

BIOS 407 Biology of Cells & Organelles (3 cr)

BIOS 426 Systems Biology (3 cr)

BIOS 444 Geomicrobiology (GEOL 444) (3 cr)

BIOS 447 Soil Microbiology (AGRO 460) (3 cr)

BIOS 477 Bioinformatics & Molecular Evolution (3 cr)

BIOS 487 Field Parasitology (4 cr)

BIOS 497 Environmental Microbiology (3 cr)

FDST 405 Food Microbiology (BIOS 445) (3 cr)

FDST 406 Food Microbiology Lab (BIOS 446) (2 cr)

FDST 415 Molds & Mycotoxins in Food, Feed, & the Human Environment (3 cr)

FDST 455 Microbiology of Fermented Foods (2 cr)

FDST 455L Microbiology of Fermented Foods Lab (1 cr)

NOTE: FDST 455L is offered even years only.

PLPT 369 Introductory Plant Pathology (BIOS 369) (3 cr)

PLPT 369L Introductory Plant Pathology Lab (1 cr)

PLPT 370 Biology of Fungi (AGRO 370/HORT 370) (3 cr)

VBMS 303 Principles & Prevention of Livestock Diseases (3 cr)

VBMS 408 Functional Histology (BIOS 408) (4 cr)

VBMS 424 Basic Molecular Infectious Diseases (3 cr)

NOTE: VBMS 424 is offered odd years only.

VBMS 441 Pathogenic Microbiology (BIOS 441) (3 cr)

Within the same subject matter area, students may request substitution for an elective course at the 300 level or above.

Minimum Credit Hours for Graduation – 120 cr

Program Assessment. To gauge the effectiveness of the program, majors within their senior year will be required to complete selected assessment activities.

Results of participation in these assessment activities will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

Students majoring in microbiology may not take any of the courses required for the major in microbiology as Pass/No Pass except for courses involving independent study, research, and seminars.

Nutrition & Health Sciences: Community Health and Wellness Option

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

MAJOR: Nutrition & Health Sciences: Community Health and Wellness Option

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

ADVISOR: Victoria Fisher

DESCRIPTION

The Community Health and Wellness option is designed for those students interested in health education and health promotion. Graduates are prepared to promote healthy lifestyles and enhance the quality of life for individuals and communities while working in a variety of settings to include worksite and health promotion programs, schools, public health agencies, nonprofit health organizations, and voluntary health agencies (American Heart Association, American Cancer Society, etc.) This option is also appropriate for students interested in pursuing graduate programs in such areas as public health, health policy, and other related areas. Upon completion of the option, students will be eligible to sit for the Certified Health Education Specialist (CHES) exam./ins>

Degree at a Glance

All courses must be taken for a grade.

ACE Requirements 35

ACE 1. 3

ACE 2. 3

ACE 3. *STAT 218 or *EDPS 459 3

ACE 4. *CHEM 109 4

ACE 5. 3

ACE 6. *PSYC 181 4

ACE 7. 3

ACE 8. 3

ACE 9. *NUTR 253 or *SOCI 217 or *COMM 211 or *PSYC 330 3

ACE 10. *NUTR 487 6

* Signifies where a course counts toward both major and ACE requirements.

< Only grades of C or above count towards graduation requirements for NUTR courses.

Professional Requirements 43

NUTR 100, NUTR 250, NUTR 252, NUTR 256, NUTR 302, NUTR 352, NUTR 356, NUTR 400, NUTR 404, NUTR 406, NUTR 407, NUTR 408, (3 hrs ea) 36

NUTR 150 2

NUTR 344 4

Supporting Courses 21-24

MATH 101 or higher 2-5

SOCI 252 or SOCI 353 3

BIOS 111 4

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L 4

CHEM 110 4

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L 4

Selectives 9

Select from: COMM 271, COMM 354, COMM 370, CYAF 446, PSYC 265, PSYC 289, PSYC 428, PSYC 471, SOCI 252, SOCI 325, SOCI 353, SOCI 443, GERO 200

Electives 9-12

Total Hours 120

ACE Requirements

All UNL students will be required to complete a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas. These can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of classes they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO). There may be required courses within a program that will also satisfy ACE requirements. Therefore, it is highly recommended that students contact their advisor prior to registering for ACE classes in order to insure that each of the class selections are in the best interest of the students' academic program.

Pre-Veterinary Medicine

COLLEGE: Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

MAJOR: Pre-Veterinary Medicine

DEGREE OFFERED: Non-degree seeking only

HOURS REQUIRED: 60-70

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: Usually 2.50

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

ADVISOR: Michael Carlson

DESCRIPTION

Director: Donald L. Reynolds, School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences, 120C Vet Basic Sciences

Head: Larry Berger, Department of Animal Science, C203 Animal Sciences

Individuals wishing to pursue a career as a veterinarian must earn a Doctor of Veterinary Medicine (DVM) degree or its equivalent from an accredited school or college of veterinary medicine (S/CVM). Qualification for admission to a S/CVM includes the successful completion of a pre-veterinary medicine program (PVET). The PVET program includes academic and non-academic requirements. This listing focuses on academic requirements. Non-academic requirements may be found on individual S/CVM websites.

Academic requirements are published on individual S/CVM websites, which include specific undergraduate courses required for admission and PVET academic performance standards. College-level courses that meet PVET requirements are specified by each S/CVM. The focus of the UNL PVET program is on courses required for admission to the Professional Program in Veterinary Medicine (PPVM), a cooperative program between the University of Nebraska–Lincoln and Iowa State University. However, it may be modified to help a student qualify for admission to any S/CVM.

The UNL PVET program is not a degree-granting program. Expect it to take 2-3 years to complete it.

Pass/No Pass credits are not accepted. PVET courses must be taken for a grade, unless the course is only offered Pass/No Pass.

A grade of a C or better is necessary to fulfill the PVET requirement. If a course is repeated to obtain a higher grade or to earn a grade of C or better, the average of all grades earned for that course will be included in the admission assessment.

The acceptability of AP, CLEP, or IB earned credits varies by S/CVM and each S/CVM publishes its policy on its website.

Each PVET student is encouraged to pursue a baccalaureate degree in a degree program of his or her choice concurrent with pursuing the PVET program. Individuals with a baccalaureate degree need only to complete the PVET program requirements to qualify for admission to a S/CVM..

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

PPVM Pre-Veterinary Medicine Core

NOTE: What follows fulfills the PVET requirements for the Professional Program in Veterinary Medicine (PPVM), a cooperative program between the University of Nebraska–Lincoln and Iowa State University. Criteria for admission to that program may be found on the PPVM website at http://vetmed.unl.edu/prospectivestudents. Students planning to attend other veterinary schools must check with those schools to determine if there are any differences between the other veterinary school and the PPVM PVET requirements.

College Integrative Course 3

AGRI 103 Introduction to Agricultural & Natural Resource Systems (NRES 103) 3

Veterinary Science 1

VBMS 101 Success in Veterinary Science 1

Natural Science Courses 38-40

Life Sciences 8

LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L Fundamentals of Biology I & Lab (ACE 4) 4

LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L Fundamentals of Biology II & Lab (ACE 4) 4

NOTE: BIOS 101/101L and BIOS 112/112L or their equivalents will not satisfy this requirement.

Genetics 4

AGRO 315 Genetics or BIOS 206 General Genetics 4

Anatomy and Physiology 4-8

Select two from the following options:

Option 1: ASCI 240 Anatomy & Physiology of Domestic Animals 4

Option 2: BIOS 213 Human Physiology 3 and BIOS 214 Human Anatomy 5 or VBMS 407 Introduction to Veterinary Anatomy 4

Chemistry 15

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I (ACE 4) 4

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II (ACE 4) 4

CHEM 251 Organic Chemistry I 3

CHEM 252 Organic Chemistry II 3

CHEM 253 Organic Chemistry I Lab or CHEM 254 Organic Chemistry II Lab 1

Physics 5

Select from:

PHYS 141 Elementary General Physics I (ACE 4) 5

PHYS 211 & PHYS 221 General Physics I & Lab 5

NOTE: PHYS 151 and MSYM 109/109L do not meet the requirement

Biological Chemistry 3

Select from:

BIOC 321 Elements of Biochemistry 3

BIOC 431 Biomolecules & Metabolism (BIOS 431/CHEM 431) 3

Mathematics and Statistics 5

Five credit hours beyond MATH 101 College Algebra

Select from:

MATH 102 Trigonometry 2

MATH 103 College Algebra & Trigonometry 5 (only 2 credit hours apply)

MATH 104 Applied Calculus 3

MATH 106 Calculus I 5

STAT 218 Introduction to Statistics (ACE 3) 3

Communications 9

Written Communication(ACE 1) 6

Select two from:

ENGL 150 Writing: Rhetoric as Inquiry 3

ENGL 151 Writing: Rhetoric as Argument 3

ENGL 254 Writing and Communities 3

JGEN 120 Basic Business Communication 3

JGEN 200 Technical Communication I 3

JGEN 300 Technical Communication II 3

Oral Communication (ACE 2) 3

Select one from:

COMM 109 Fundamentals of Human Communication 3

COMM 209 Public Speaking 3

COMM 283 Interpersonal Communication 3

COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication 3

Economics (ACE 6) 3

Select one from:

AECN 141 Introduction to the Economics of Agriculture 3

ECON 200 Economic Essentials and Issues 3

ECON 211/ECON 211H Principles of Macroeconomics 3

ECON 212/ECON 212H Principles of Microeconomics 3

ACE Courses 12

Select one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 7, 8, and 9.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

All courses should be taken for a letter grade, unless the course is only offered Pass/No Pass (P/N). A course taken P/N may either be not accepted or accepted as if the student earned a C for that course.

Minimal grade requirement

A grade of at least a C must be earned in each course.

Psychology

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Psychology

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR: Joanna Seley and Marybeth Helmink

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Rick Bevins, 238 Burnett Hall

Associate Chairs: David DiLillo and Eve Brank, 238 Burnett Hall

Professors: Belli, Bevins, Bornstein, Crockett, DiLillo, Garbin, Hansen, Hope, Leger, Molfese, Scalora, Spaulding, Tomkins, Wiener

Associate Professors: Brank, Dodd, Gervais, Li, McChargue, Nelson, Schutte, Stoltenberg, Willis-Esqueda

Assistant Professors: Brock, Johnson, Neta, Stevens

Assistant Professor of Practice: Williamson

The undergraduate degree program in psychology is designed to provide you with educational and research experiences that can prepare you for graduate or professional school in academic psychology, medicine, dentistry, nursing, public health, and law—to name a few. The bachelors degree program in psychology can also prepare you for diverse careers in applied fields such as counseling, business, and health and human services. If you plan to major in psychology, we recommend that you meet with our advisors as early as possible to plan a program of study consistent with your interests and goals.

Graduate Work. Graduate programs leading to the doctor of philosophy degree in psychology are offered. A detailed description of these courses appears in the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Core Requirements 21

PSYC 100 Career Planning for Psychology Majors 1

PSYC 181 Introduction to Psychology 4

PSYC 263 Introduction to Cognitive Processes 3

PSYC 273 Brain & Behavior 3

PSYC 288 The Psychology of Social Behavior 3

PSYC 289 Developmental Psychology 3

PSYC 350 Research Methods & Data Analysis 4

Advanced Psychology Courses 15

15 additional credit hours in PSYC courses at the 300 level or above, including at least 9 credit hours at the 400 level or above (excluding PSYC 350, PSYC 396, PSYC 399H, PSYC 496, PSYC 497, PSYC 499).

Total credit hours: 36

NOTE: Students are strongly advised to complete Core Requirements before the Advanced Psychology Courses.

Program Assessment. To assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, the following learning outcomes will be regularly assessed:

1. Demonstrate knowledge of the main content areas of psychology, including cognitive, developmental, neuroscience and social.

2. Understand the most common research designs and demonstrate ability to locate, understand, and evaluate a published research report.

3. Generate a research report including the methodology and data analysis used to test an empirical hypothesis.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

Excluding PSYC 100, up to 3 hours of Pass/No Pass credit may be taken in major requirements.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A (1 minor):

PSYC 181
14 credit hours at the 200 level or above, including at least 9 credit hours at the 300 level or above.

Minimum: 18 credit hours

Plan B (2 minors):

PSYC 181
Plus three other courses at the 200 level or above.

Minimum: 12 credit hours.

No more than 3 hours from the following courses can count toward the minor: PSYC 296, PSYC 297, PSYC 299, PSYC 396, PSYC 496, PSYC 497, PSYC 499. Students minoring in this department may take up to 3 hours Pass/No Pass.

Russian (ASC)

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Russian (ASC)

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

ADVISOR: Radha Balasubramanian

DESCRIPTION

Chair: TBD, 1111 Oldfather Hall

Vice Chair: TBD

Professors: Balasubramanian, Hayden-Roy, Pereira, Stump

Associate Professors: Amano, Brantner, González, González-Allende, Guevara, Lorenzo, Mejias-Bikandi, Shirer, Velázquez

Assistant Professors: Enkin, Hasan, Kingsbury Brunetto, Peterson

Emeriti Professors: Carr, Fouletier-Smith, E. Jacobson, M. Jacobson, Martinez, Nickel, Saskova-Pierce, Turner, Wilhelmsen

The Department of Modern Languages and Literatures offers courses in Arabic, German, Japanese, the Romance Language group (French, Spanish), and the Slavic group (Czech, Russian). Whenever possible, the courses are conducted in the language that is studied. The aim of instruction is reading, writing, aural and oral proficiency, and an understanding of the life, literature, and culture of the country. Lectures and films in the language studied are offered during the school year for the benefit of the students in the department. Language laboratories supplement class work.

Placement

Incoming students who wish to enter the University’s language program in French, Spanish, and German are required to take the Computer Assisted Placement Examination (CAPE). The results of the placement exam, together with training in a secondary school university, or other prior second language environments, will assist students in finding the level at which they will have the greatest opportunity for success. The examination results will be used in combination with advising to determine appropriate placement in the sequence of courses offered within the department’s curriculum. CAPE is administered in the language laboratory (302 Burnett Hall). Those students exempted from this requirement are expected to enroll in a first semester elementary course (101). Students qualifying for this exemption are defined as follows:

1. Students with no previous second language exposure whatsoever.

2. Students whose second language exposure amounts to one year or less at the U.S. high school level.

3. Students who wish to begin study of a new language other than those previously studied.

Foreign language placement guidelines are generally determined by the following criteria for students who come to the University with:

1. One semester of a language in high school should take 101 (same language or a new one);

2. Two or three semesters in high school should take 102 (same language);

3. Four or five semesters in high school should take 201;

4. Six semesters in high school should take 202;

5. Eight semesters or more in high school should take 203.

The department participates in the following interdisciplinary study programs: Institute for Ethnic Studies, Global Studies, Jewish Studies, Latin American Studies, Medieval and Renaissance Studies, and Women’s and Gender Studies.

Students may receive full credit at the University of Nebraska for education abroad programs in many countries, among these are Costa Rica, France, Germany, Spain, Russia, Japan, and the Czech Republic. See http://educationabroad.unl.edu for a guide to these programs.

Auditing. Audits are allowed in 101 in French, German and Spanish only upon recommendation of the Modern Language Placement Advisors. Otherwise no audits are allowed in 100- and 200-level classes.

Literature in Translation

The Department offers the following literature in translation courses for which no knowledge of a foreign language is necessary. Check the Office of the University Registrar's website at registrar.unl.edu to determine which are being taught in any given semester:

MODL 101 Windows to the World (GLST 101)

MODL 234D Major Themes in World Literature (ENGL 234D)

MODL 298, MODL 398 Special Topics

FREN 282 and GERM 282 French/German Literature in Translation

SPAN 264 & SPAN 265 Spanish-American Literature in Translation I & II

JAPN 331 Introduction to Japanese Film

JAPN 483 Modern Japanese Literature & Culture in Translation

RUSS 482 & RUSS 483 Russian Literature in Translation I & II

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy are offered in French, German, and Spanish. For details, see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

Courses numbered 300 or above with at least 6 hours at the 400 level 27

RUSS 301, RUSS 302, RUSS 303, RUSS 304, RUSS 408 (3 hrs ea) 15

Additional hours of RUSS courses above 300 6

Russian Area Studies 6

Select from the following list or as approved by the major advisor:

HIST 330

HIST 338

HIST 362

HIST 462

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required to assemble a portfolio. A faculty advisor will inform students of the required contents of the portfolio, deadlines and procedures. During their last semester, Russian majors will be required to provide oral and written materials for their portfolios.

Results of participation in this assessment activity will in no way affect a student’s GPA or graduation.

Minor Requirement

A minor is required and may be taken in any area.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

No courses in the department may be taken by students majoring or minoring in modern languages for Pass/No Pass credit.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

12 hours in one language at the 300 level or 400 level, including at least 6 hours from 301, 302, 303, 304, and 3 hours at the 400 level.

Pass/No Pass. No courses in the department may be taken by students majoring or minoring in modern languages for Pass/No Pass credit.

Software Engineering

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Software Engineering

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 124

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.4 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

ADVISOR: Charles Riedesel

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Matthew Dwyer, 256 Avery Hall

Professors: Deogun, Dwyer, Elbaum, Goddard, Jiang, Ramamurthy, Reichenbach, Revesz, Rothermel, Samal, Seth (emeritus), Sincovec (emeritus), Surkan (emeritus), Variyam

Associate Professors: Choueiry, Cohen, Cooper, Costello (emeritus), Lu, Scott, Soh, Srisa-an, Vuran, Xu

Assistant Professors: Bradley, Cui, Detweiler, Duncan, Pierobon, Wei, Yan, Yu

Research Associate Professor: Swanson

Research Assistant Professors: Bockelman, Tian

Associate Professor of Practice: Person

Assistant Professors of Practice: Bourke, Hasan, Riedesel

Adjunct Associate Professor: Sarma

Lecturers: Patrick, Suing

Undergraduate Advisor: Charles Riedesel, 402-472-3486, chuckr@unl.edu

The UNL Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) offers Nebraska's only comprehensive program of higher education, research, and service outreach in computer science, computer engineering, and software engineering.

The CSE department offers a unique and challenging baccalaureate degree program in software engineering, incorporating hands-on learning and an integrated computer science and software engineering core curriculum to prepare graduates for professional practice in a wide range of industries and for post-graduate education.

Software engineers work on multidisciplinary teams to identify and formulate software solutions and maintain software intensive systems of all sizes. The focus of this program is on the rigorous engineering practices necessary to build, maintain and protect modern software intensive systems. Consistent with this focus, the software engineering baccalaureate program consists of a rigorous curriculum of science, math, computer science, and software engineering courses. Students completing the major will have the ability to:

Apply disciplined software engineering practices and principles to the design, architecture, development, analysis, testing and maintenance of complex software systems to meet the desired needs of the stakeholders and within realistic constraints.
Identify, formulate and solve engineering problems using computational resources.
Contribute their expertise to the solution of problems by effectively collaborating and communicating with other stakeholders in multidisciplinary teams.
Adapt to rapid advances in computing and software engineering tools, technologies, principles and practices.

Students will also have:

The background and perspective for post-graduate education. Studies develop skills in the application of theory, experimentation, and life-long learning/professional development.
Insight into the world of practicing professionals for collaborations, mutual support, and representing the profession to government and society. Studies include teamwork, communication, and hands-on experience, plus students are provided with multiple opportunities for involvement in organizations such as ACM, UPE, and IEEE.

The CSE department also offers a degree of bachelor of science in computer engineering through the College of Engineering, and a bachelor of science in computer science through the College of Arts and Sciences. All students majoring in the CSE department should see their advisors during the first semester to ensure they understand the differences in the requirements between the three majors. Majors should consult with their advisors each semester for registration advising.

Introductory Courses. Entering students take SOFT 160 Software Engineering I, the first course in the software engineering core series (SOFT 160, SOFT 161, SOFT 260, SOFT 261). This course provides an introduction to fundamental software engineering concepts and foundational computer science topics to prepare students for more advanced software engineering and computer science courses.

Graduate Programs. The CSE Department offers several graduate degree programs: master of science in computer science, master of science in computer science with a computer engineering specialization, master of science in computer science with a bioinformatics specialization, doctor of philosophy in computer science, doctor of philosophy in engineering with computer engineering specialization, doctor of philosophy in computer science with bioinformatics specialization, and joint doctor of philosophy in computer science and mathematics. See the Graduate Studies Bulletin for details.

MAJOR DEPARTMENT ADMISSION

Students are expected to meet minimum college entrance requirements. After being admitted to the college, students desiring to pursue a degree in software engineering must go through the Professional Admission process, which is automatically performed for qualifying students at the end of the sophomore year. In order to be considered for Professional Admission to the software engineering program, students must receive at least a C+ in SOFT 160, SOFT 161, SOFT 260, SOFT 261, CSCE 235, MATH 106, and MATH 107 and a GPA of at least 2.5 (semester and cumulative). If a student's cumulative GPA drops below 2.4, the student may be placed on restricted status, may be removed from the College, and may not be able to graduate.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

The software engineering degree requires 124 hours of course work. There is a set of required core courses and technical elective courses in computer science and software engineering (79 credit hours), mathematics (18 credit hours), science (12 credit hours), and other supporting courses (15 credit hours) as described below.

Computer Science and Software Engineering 79

Computer Science Core 23

CSCE 10, CSCE 230, CSCE 235, CSCE 322, CSCE 378, CSCE 411, CSCE 423, CSCE 451, CSCE 491

Software Engineering Core 29

SOFT 160, SOFT 161, SOFT 260, SOFT 261, SOFT 360, SOFT 461, SOFT 466, SOFT 467, SOFT 468

Technical Electives 15

Students must take at least 15 credit hours of SOFT or CSCE technical electives. At least 9 hours must be taken at the 400 level except SOFT and CSCE courses required by the software engineering major and except courses that have been designated as courses that will not count toward a major or minor in computer science or software engineering by the Department of Computer Science and Engineering.

Included courses at the 200-level are: CSCE 236.

Included courses at the 300-level are: CSCE 335, CSCE 351, CSCE 396, CSCE 399H.

In addition to the courses mention above, excluded CSCE designated courses are: CSCE 401H, CSCE 402H, CSCE 488, CSCE 489, CSCE 490, CSCE 493. Honors versions of these courses are also not allowed to count towards technical elective credits.

Capstone Experience 12

CSCE 493 (2 semesters, 3 hours each) and CSCE 486 and CSCE 487 in strict sequence.

Mathematics 18

MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 314, STAT 380 15

Select one of the following: 3

MATH 208, MATH 208H, MATH 238, MATH 428, MATH 439, MATH 465 or an approved statistics course (choose from STAT 412, STAT 414, STAT 442, STAT 450)

Science 12

Must take at least 12 credit hours of science courses intended for science/engineering majors and must include at least one laboratory. The CSE department has identified the following five disciplines with their acceptable courses:

Chemistry: CHEM 109 & CHEM 110 or CHEM 113 & CHEM 114 and CHEM 221, CHEM 261, CHEM 262, CHEM 263, CHEM 264

Physics and Astronomy: PHYS 141, PHYS 142, PHYS 211, PHYS 221, PHYS 212, PHYS 222, PHYS 213, PHYS 223, ASTR 204, ASTR 224

Biological Sciences: BIOS 205, BIOS 206, BIOS 207, LIFE 120 & LIFE 120L, LIFE 121 & LIFE 121L

Earth and Atmospheric Sciences: GEOG 155, GEOG 181, GEOL 101, GEOL 103, GEOL 210, GEOL 211, GEOL 310, GEOL 340, METR 100, METR 205, METR 223, METR 311, METR 312, METR 323, METR 341

Anthropology: ANTH 242, ANTH 242L

NOTE: Bold face type indicates a lab course or that a lab is included with the course.

Other Supporting Courses 15

ENGR 20, JGEN 200, and ACE 5, 6, 7, and 9.

Program Assessment. In order to assist the department in evaluating the effectiveness of its programs, majors will be required in their senior year to complete a written exit survey. Results of participation in these assessment activities will in no way affect a student's GPA or graduation.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Applicants for Professional Admission to software engineering must meet the usual college requirements plus a minimum grade rule on the following core courses (or their equivalents):

Grades of C+ or higher in CSCE 235, MATH 106, MATH 107, SOFT 160, SOFT 161, SOFT 260, and SOFT 261.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Students majoring in software engineering may not take any course from the list of core computer science courses, core software engineering courses, capstone courses, or from the list of technical electives for Pass/No Pass credit.